Guide to the Paul Kwilecki photographs and papers, circa 1910-2008, bulk 1960-2008 RL.00790
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Religion, 1965-2000; 8 folders 110 prints
  - House of worship, West Bainbridge, 2000 Feb. (Box PHO 7, Print 4-200-20)
  - Church for sale, 1998 Apr. (Box PHO 7, Print 22-498-20)
  - Communion service, Nelson Chapel, A.M.E. Church, 1998 Mar. (Box PHO 7, Print 14-398-18)
  - 129th anniversary ceremony, Nelson Chapel, A.M.E. Church, 1998 Mar. (Box PHO 7, Print 12-398-4a)
  - 129th anniversary ceremony, Nelson Chapel, A.M.E. Church, 1998 Mar. (Box PHO 7, Print 12-398-23)
  - No known title, 1984 December (Box PHO 28, Print 64-1284)
  - No known title, 1983 November (Box PHO 28, Print 65-1183)
  - No known title (Box PHO 28, Print unnumbered)
  - No known title, 2002 February (Box PHO 28, Print unnumbered)
  - No known title, 1983 August (Box PHO 28, Print 45-883-25a)
  - Baptism, Mt. Zuma, 1977 ( Understandings), 1977 April (Box PHO 28, Print 18-477-30a)
  - Preacher standing by poster, [circa 1965] (Oversize-box 2, Print unnumbered)
    This preacher is standing in the anteroom of his small church. Once I didn't like this picture. Now I do.
  - Rev. Mitchell preaching prior to baptizing in Mt. Zuma's brand new pool, 1982 Apr. (Oversize-box 2, Print 38-482-9a)
  - Rev. Mitchell preaching to the children before baptism, 1982 Apr. (Oversize-box 2, Print 36-482-16)
  - First baptism in Mt. Zuma's new pool behind church, 1982 Apr. (Oversize-box 2, Print 38-482-14a)
    Rev. Mitchell, left; Ben Edwards, right.
  - Sunday morning church service. Camilla, Ga., 1984 Jan. (Oversize-box 2, Print 2-84-26)
- Portraits, 1962-1985; 1 folders 7 prints
  - Self-portrait taken at the request of a magazine, 1985 Dec. (Box PHO 6, Print 51-1285-11)
  - Grace Kohnke in her dining room, 1985 Sept. (Box PHO 6, Print 37-38-8-985)
  - Portrait of Classie Heard in her bedroom, 1962 (Box PHO 6, Print unnumbered)
    This was one of the first portraits I attempted. It was made inside a very old house out in the county (near Cyrene). This woman is the granddaughter and great-granddaughter of the men shown in the photograph above her head.
  - Marie Dixon in her dining room where she worked until her death on her memoirs, 1983 Feb. (Box PHO 6, Print 8-283-17a)
    See my notes about Marie and this and another photo.
  - Rheda Mae Jackson in her living room, 1983 Jan. (Box PHO 6, Print 3-183-11a)
    See my notes for details about Rheda and the making of this picture.
  - Dr. Ehrlich in his treatment room, 1975 [mounted on board] (Oversize-box 1, Print unnumbered)
    Dr. M. A. Ehrlich in his operating room on his 75th birthday. He and his brother had this small downtown clinic years ago. As I took his picture he reminisced about times gone by. See my notes for more on this.
  - Woman sitting in window in burned house, circa 1963 [mounted on board] (Oversize-box 1, Print unnumbered)
    This was an early effort, not fully successful but not altogether a failure either.
- Workers, 1965-1990; 2 folders 32 prints
  - Tenant farmer resting in his front yard, 1983 Apr. (Box PHO 9, Print 18-483-26)
    This is one of my favorite photographs. See my notes for more information on this man.
  - Watt Baldwin, Jr. in his garage, 1980 June (Box PHO 9, Print 59-680-23a)
  - Log yard worker on a fork lift, 1990 May (Box PHO 9, Print 10-590-32)
    Log yards broker pulp wood between the grower and the consumer (paper mills).
  - Man in weigh-in station at Elberta Crate and Box Co., 1984 May (Box PHO 9, Print 29-584)
  - Elberta Crate and Box Co., 1981 Nov. (Box PHO 9, Print 134-1181-8)
  - Construction worker tearing down an old building (Belks), 1983 Oct. (Box PHO 9, Print 49-1083-26)
  - Livestock auction, 1982 Mar. (Box PHO 9, Print 23-382-20)
  - Tractor driver standing inside peanut warehouse, 1989 June (Box PHO 9, Print 43-989-7a)
    Pile of peanuts is visible behind him.
  - Fork lift operator on a log yard, 1989 Jan. (Box PHO 9, Print 1-1-89)
  - Elberta Crate and Box Co., 1981 Nov. (Box PHO 9, Print 134-1181-7)
  - Dollar Farm Products Co., 1989 Aug. (Box PHO 9, Print 40-889-25)
    This man drives a tractor during peanut season and a truck the rest of the year.
  - Dollar Farm Products Co., 1989 Aug. (Box PHO 9, Print 38-889-32)
    This man has been on top of a rail car loading corn from storage bins.
  - Elberta Crate and Box Co., 1982 Jan. (Box PHO 9, Print 2-182-32)
  - Man in field holding basket of bell peppers. Decatur County, 1984 June (Box PHO 9, Print 34-684)
  - Resting in the field, 1983 July (Box PHO 9, Print 36-783-26a)
    Resting in the field while the big machine turns around at the end of a row.
  - Picking bell peppers, 1984 June (Box PHO 9, Print 37-684-9)
  - Bell pepper pickers, 1984 June (Box PHO 9, Print 38-684-25A)
  - Maids in a room of the Stephen Decatur Hotel shortly before it was torn down, 1970 (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
  - Prostitute standing in doorway of her house, 1965 (Box PHO 9, Print No#)
    The building is the oldest structure in Bainbridge, so this is a picture of the oldest profession in front of the oldest building. Is she eyeing me as a prospective customer or just sizing me up?
  - Dr. M. A. Ehrlich in the doorway of his office, 1980 Aug. (Box PHO 9, Print 78-880-11)
  - Cecil Mills in his barbershop, 1970 (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
  - Stoker at Elberta Crate Co., circa 1970 (Oversize-box 2, Print unnumbered)
    This man stoked the boilers at Elberta Crate Co. back in the days when boilers were stoked. Refreshingly, he is the opposite of cosmetic. Real.
  - Elberta Crate Co., 1981 Dec. (Oversize-box 2, Print 147-1281-10)
  - Horace Battles at Elberta Crate Co., 1981 Dec. (Oversize-box 2, Print 141-1281-3)
    He managed the boilers and blew the whistle. See my notes for more details.
  - Loggers in the woods near Attapulgus, 1978 Feb. (Oversize-box 2, Print 19-278-12)
  - No known title (Box PHO 28, Print unnumbered)
  - No known title (Box PHO 28, Print unnumbered)
  - No known title, 1979 November (Box PHO 28, Print 162-1179-27)
  - No known title, 1979 September (Box PHO 28, Print 113-979-25)
  - No known title, 1975 (Box PHO 28, Print unnumbered)
  - No known title (Box PHO 28, Print unnumbered)
  - No known title, 1989 August (Box PHO 28, Print 40-889-18)
- Trailways Bus Station, 1977-1980; 1 folders 16 prints
  - Woman, boy, juke box, 1978 ( Understandings) (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
  - Trailways Bus Station, 1978 Aug. (Box PHO 9, Print 56-878-33)
  - Family, Trailways Bus Station, 1978 May (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
  - Exterior, Trailways Bus Station, 1977 Nov. (Box PHO 9, Print 130-1177-20)
  - Trailways Bus Station, 1978 Sept. (Box PHO 9, Print 70-978-23)
  - Trailways Bus Station, 1977 Sept. (Box PHO 9, Print 104-977-7a)
  - Trailways Bus Station, 1980 July ( Understandings) (Box PHO 9, Print 65-780-12)
  - Trailways Bus Station, 1978 Jan. ( Understandings) (Box PHO 9, Print 1-1-78-23a)
  - Trailways Bus Station, 1977 Dec. (Box PHO 9, Print 138-1277-35)
  - Trailways Bus Station, 1978 Aug. (Box PHO 9, Print 68-878-7.5)
  - Colored waiting room. Trailways Bus Station, 1978 Jan. (Box PHO 9, Print 1-1-78-5a)
  - Scales in the waiting room. Trailways Bus Station, 1980 Jan. (Box PHO 9, Print 5-180-6)
  - Phone,Trailways Bus station, 1978 Jan. (Box PHO 9, Print 1-1-78-13A)
  - No known title, circa May 1982 (Box PHO 27, Print 48-582-10A)
    Uncaptioned black-and-white print of middle-aged white man, with one arm, sitting in Trailways bus office behind work counter. Date derived from wall calendar appearing in the image.
  - No known title, 1976 November (Box PHO 28, Print 118-1176-11A)
  - Manager of the Trailways Bus Station, 1982 May (Box PHO 28, Print 48-582-10A)
- Stores, 1967-1987; 1 folders 24 prints
  - Mrs. Tomlinson in the house of tomatoes, 1967 (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
  - Ms. Bennet in her jewelry store on West Street, 1978 Oct. ( Understandings) (Box PHO 9, Print 89-1078-9)
  - Window display in McCrory's 5 cent and 10 cent store, 1978 Nov. ( Understandings) (Box PHO 9, Print 102-1178)
  - Outside entrance to Wynn's Department Store, 1968 Dec. (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
  - Ms. Sasser in her grocery store, 1979 Oct.( Understandings) (Box PHO 9, Print 135-1079-22)
  - Interior of Jake's Pawn Shop on Water Street, 1968 (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
    Young man is making a weekly payment.
  - Religious pictures for sale at Elmore's Department Store, 1978 Nov. (Box PHO 9, Print 103-1178 10a)
  - Mr. Gause in his Pure Oil Station, 1980 May (Box PHO 9, Print 49-580-12a)
  - Hart-Rollins Furniture Co. Broad Street, 1981 Jan. (Box PHO 9, Print 16-181-15)
  - Façade of the Men's Shop, 1970 (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
    Originally operated by Willie Jim Brockett.
  - Broad Street, McCrory's Diana Shops, 1967 (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
    View of Broad Street from Willis Park.
  - Neighborhood grocery and meat market, 1987 Aug. (Box PHO 9, Print 9-887-34)
  - 1981 Mar. (Box PHO 9, Print 37-381-26)
    Tiny store near school in West Bainbridge where children go to buy candy, etc. Also neighborhood grocery. This is the proprietor.
  - Mr. Ward in the window of his hardware store, 1968 (Box PHO 9, Print unnumbered)
  - Woman and baby in laundromat in Bainbridge Mall, 1973 (Oversize-box 2, Print unnumbered)
  - No known title (Box PHO 28, Print unnumbered)
  - No known title (Box PHO 28, Print unnumbered)
  - No known title, 1979 January (Box PHO 28, Print 11-179)
  - No known title, 1981 February (Box PHO 28, Print 22-281-21A)
  - No known title, 1980 May (Box PHO 28, Print 48-580-16A)
  - No known title, 1979 January (Box PHO 28, Print 9-179-1)
  - No known title (Box PHO 28, Print unnumbered)
  - No title known, 1981 August (Box PHO 28, Print 101-881-16)
  - No known title, 1979 April (Box PHO 28, Print 44-479)
- Additional Unidentified Prints
  Five black-and-white 11x14 inch prints were added to the collection in 2017. They are untitled and undated, although one has been tentatively dated from a wall calendar. One entry was listed under the Trailways Bus Station series, as it is a portrait of an employee in a Trailways office. The other four are listed here and are undated and uncaptioned; their intended series is uncertain.
  - No known title (Box PHO 27, Print 44-479)
    Undated, uncaptioned black-and-white print of main street in commercial district of an unknown town, probably Bainbridge, Georgia. View is of store window with mannequin in wedding dress, in left foreground; music store, various other stores in background.
  - No known title (Box PHO 27, Print unnumbered)
    Undated, uncaptioned black-and-white print of close-up of giant tree, foreground, behind low iron fence, with partial view of white frame house in right background.
  - No known title (Box PHO 27, Print 72-579)
    Undated, uncaptioned black-and-white print of two African American women and one child fishing on river bank. May have been part of the Flint River series.
  - No known title (Box PHO 27, Print unnumbered)
    Undated, uncaptioned black-and-white print of middle-aged white man with magnification glasses, perhaps a jeweler, seated at a workbench with office clock in background. May have been part of the Portraits series.
- Prints by Photographer David Vestal
  - Cape Cod, Photographs by David Vestal, Quadrant Prints (in large portfolio), 1960s?, 6 prints, some age damage (Oversize-box 2)
  - David Vestal prints and correspondence, 1940s-2007; 13 prints 4 folders (Box PHO 29)
    David Vestal sent these black-and-white imagbes printed on paper to Paul Kwilecki as part of an ongoing exchange of ideas and comments about photography. According to a 2004 letter included in one of these packets of images, Vestal was apparently working on a book, possibly about photography technique. This group includes 13 paper prints dating from his earliest work in the 1940s to 2003, signed and including the negative number, location, and date. There is also a note (2206) and a letter to Kwilecki (2004). Some of the prints are copyrighted 2007. Most include a sheet of paper with Vestal's comments on the shot.
- Contact Sheets, 1976-2002 and undated; 8 Linear Feet 16 boxes; 333 folders approximately 1330 contact sheets
  Series contains Kwilecki's gelatin silver contact sheets, received after his death and arranged in chronological order by year and within, roughly by months. The sheets come in two sizes: 8x10 and 11x14 inches. The years 1976 to 1979 only come in the smaller size; later years have both sizes or only 11x14. Almost all the sheets were marked by Kwilecki with the roll number and year (last two digits), but some are undated. There are very few editorial markings such as frame selections or notes.
  Kwilecki's most prolific years spanned the 1970s and 1980s, and this is borne out by the number of contact sheets he created from his 35 mm and 120 mm negative rolls during this period. From 1976 to 1999 Kwilecki created roughly 60-140 sheets each year. Some years (1990 and 1995 in particular) many fewer are found in the collection. The years 2000 to 2002 reflect a slowing-down of photographic output with only a few folders each.
  - 1976-1977, 49 folders (Box PHO 11, Box PHO 12)
  - 1978-1979, 54 folders (Box PHO 13, Box PHO 14, Box PHO 15)
  - 1980-1981, 55 folders (Box PHO 15, Box PHO 16, Box PHO 17, Box PHO 18)
  - 1982-1983, 42 folders (Box PHO 18, Box PHO 19, Box PHO 20)
  - 1984-1985, 24 folders (Box PHO 20, Box PHO 21)
  - 1986-1989, 27 folders (Box PHO 21, Box PHO 22)
  - 1990-1994, 31 folders (Box PHO 23, Box PHO 24)
  - 1995-1996, 13 folders (Box PHO 23, Box PHO 24)
  - 1997-2002, 36 folders (Box PHO 25, Box PHO 26)
  - Undated contact sheets, 2 folders (Box PHO 24, Box PHO 26)
- Negatives (RESTRICTED), circa 1910s, 1940s-2001; 12 Linear Feet 15 boxes
  Titles come from box labels indicating location of the darkroom (termed "house" and "office") where the photographer's negatives were originally stored when collected by the library. The negatives have been given basic processing and are closed to use. Contact sheets and finished prints offer an alternative access to a selection of hundreds of Kwilecki's images.
  The negatives are in 35 mm as well as 126 mm strips; also included are some cut frames and sheet film. Contact sheets in the collection from earlier years (1970s to early 1980s) are almost exclusively in 35 mm format.
  Eleven 8x10 inch black-and-white cellulose nitrate sheet film negatives of uncertain origin were also found among the safety negatives. These were removed for preservation purposes and are slated for digitization. They may represent Kwilecki's earliest work or may be the work of another unidentified photographer, and may date to the 1940s (slated for digitization).
  Also includes two glass plate negatives of unknown provenance of a picnic or outing with men and women in a group, circa 1910s (also slated for digitization).
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Negatives are closed to use. Nitrate sheet negatives are slated for digitization.
  Finished prints derived from the negatives are available for use; additionally, over 1300 contact sheets offer an avenue of access to a larger set of thousands of images.
  Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
  - House negatives (Box NEG 1)
  - House negatives (Box NEG 2)
  - Office negatives (Box NEG 3)
  - House negatives (Box NEG 4)
  - Loose negatives (Box NEG 5)
  - 1979 negatives (Box NEG 6)
  - Office negatives (Box NEG 7)
  - House negatives (Box NEG 8)
  - House negatives (Box NEG 9)
  - House negatives (Box NEG 10)
  - Safety negatives (Box NEG 11)
  - Office negatives (Box NEG 12)
  - House negatives (Box NEG 13)
  - Glass plate negatives, circa 1910s; 2 items 5x7 inches (Box NEG 14)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Glass plate negatives are closed to use. Viewing copies may be requested in advance. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to to use these materials.
  - Sheet negatives (NITRATE), 1940s? (Box NEG 15)
    Nitrate negatives are closed to use. Viewing copies may be requested in advance. (Slated for digitization.) Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use these materials.
- Papers, 1966-2008 and undated
  Series comprises correspondence and journals (the largest groups), as well as biographical materials, writing and lectures, interviews, printing and developing notes, and printed material such as fliers, clippings, and brochures. Much of this material was received after Kwilecki's death in 2009.
  Included are interviews and speeches in which Kwilecki speaks about his publishing experience, his philosophy of photography, his love for Decatur County, his experiences as a self-taught documentary photographer, and his thoughts on the subjects and themes found in his work as a Southern photographer.
  - Correspondence and Writings, 1977-2001 and undated; 4 folders
    - Biography of Kwilecki, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - Correspondence, 1966 June-1992 April and undated, 8 folders (Box MSS 1)
    - Kwilecki interview conducted by P.J. Brownlee, 1994 Dec. 28 (Box MSS 1)
    - Restoring the Decatur County Courthouse, 1998-2000, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - La Grange talk, 1999 Feb. 17 (Box MSS 1)
    - Hog Killing at the County Farm, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - Duke lecture, 2001 Oct. 3, 2 copies (Box MSS 1)
    - The Junior-Senior Prom, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - Society for Photographic Education Talk, 1994 Nov. 5 (Box MSS 1)
      Given by Kwilecki to the Society for Photographic Education in Atlanta, Ga.
    - My Publishing Experience, 1994 Apr. 30 (Box MSS 1)
      Given by Kwilecki at the High Museum of Art in Atlanta, Ga.
    - Gallery Talk, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - Collection of Kwilecki's writings on Decatur County people, places, things and events, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - Correspondence files (Box MSS 3-13)
      Correspondence files include letters from Center for Documentary Studies faculty in Durham, North Carolina, letters from David Vestal, and other mentors. Also includes correspondence with publishers.
    - Mixed correspondence, publicity, and writings, 1971-2008 and undated (Box MSS 14-16)
    - Printing notes, 1977-1991 (Box MSS 1)
    - Printing notes, 1977-2001, 3 folders (Box MSS 17)
      Originally housed in two ring binder notebooks. The second contains detailed comments on aperture, shutter speed, darkroom techniques, and outcomes when reprinting negatives.
    - Journals, 1967 Mar. 30-1969 Oct. 14, 8 folders 1 box (Box MSS 2)
  - Printed Material, 1970-2001 and undated; 3 folders
    - Customer receipts, undated, 2 receipts (Box MSS 1)
    - Brochure: Barbara Morgan exhibition of photography, The Museum of Modern Art, New York, 1972 Mar. 8-May 31 (Box MSS 1)
    - Brochure: Discovery: Inner and Outer Worlds, Portfolio II, The Friends of Photography, Carmel, California, 1970 (Box MSS 1)
    - Brochure: Introducing Fine Photographs, undated (Box MSS 1)
    - News clipping regarding Kwilecki's exhibit, Decatur County Georgia, being shown at Duke University, 2001 (Box MSS 1)
    - Brochure: Paul Kwilecki: Decatur County, Georgia, 1994 Nov. 4-Dec. 21 (Box MSS 1)
      This exhibit was shown at Lehigh University.
    - News article honoring Kwilecki for his gift of 12 courthouse photographs to Decatur county, undated, photocopy (Box MSS 1)
    - A Decatur County Resolution honoring Kwilecki for his gift of photography, before 2009, photocopy (Box MSS 1)
    - Information regarding Kwilecki's traveling exhibit, Homage: Photographs of Decatur County, Georgia, 1997 (Box MSS 1)
    - Publicity poster for Scenes from Decatur County exhibit, Hartford, Connecticut, 2002 (signed by Kwilecki), 2 copies (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Understandings: Photographs of Decatur County, Georgia. Paul Kwilecki. Introduction by Alex Harris. Center for Documentary Photography: University of N.C. at Chapel Hill, NC, 1981 (inscribed with Jane Kwilecki's name) (Box MSS 16)
    - Photographs by Paul Kwilecki. High Museum of Art [Atlanta] Calendar of Events, 1980 Dec. (Box MSS 16)
    - The Land's People. Paul Kwilecki. American Land Forum, Volume V, No. 1, Winter 1985 (Box MSS 16)
    - Workers of Decatur County, Georgia. Paul Kwilecki. Southern Quarterly, Spring 1994 (Box MSS 16)
    - Homage: Photographs of Decatur County, Georgia. Essay by Paul Kwilecki for large-format brochure. Winthrop University galleries, South Carolina State Museum exhibits, 1997 (Box MSS 16)
  - Audiovisual Materials
    - Videocassettes, 2 VHS cassettes (Box MSS 16)
      Original recordings are closed to use; access requires production of viewing copies. Please contact the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.